# 大家好 今天天氣比較好一點哦
Hi everyone! The weather today is a bit better.
A month ago
# 來這大山里面看一下有沒 有沒這個好吃的 在這裡面
We’re coming into this mountain and see if there, there are any good snacks, any good snacks here.
# 以前這裡很多好吃的哦
There used to be a lot in the past.
# 不知道熟了沒有
But I'm not sure if they’re ripe now.
# 應該快熟啦
I think they’ll be ripe very soon.
# 沒熟也可以來這裡看一下
We can just take a look here even if they’re not.
# 這個夠大吧
This is really big, isn’t it?
# 下還很多的哦 這裡也有
Down there are a lot more, and here as well.
# 這裡有小的
Here’s a small one.
# 再去那邊 那邊有三四個好大的
Let’s go to that side as well. There are three or four really big ones.
# 看到沒有
See?
# 等它熟的時候我就過來摘
I’ll come again and pick them when they’re ripe.
# 你看 這個 這個是獼猴桃哦
Look! This is, this is kiwifruit.
# 我們這野生的猴桃是這樣子的
That’s how our wild kiwifruits here look like.
# 那麼多毛 哦 全身都長了看
It’s so furry. Oh! It’s covered with fur.
# 這個 還沒 不是很熟
It’s, it’s not, it’s not really that ripe.
# 你看 好多毛的
Look! It’s so furry.
# 哇 你看 全是毛
Wa! Look! It’s covered with fur!
# 這個還不能吃那麼快
This one can't be eaten yet. Not so soon.
# 要秋天的時候 要到冬天的時候才可以吃的 這種
Not until autumn, until winter, can they be eaten, these kind of kiwifruits.
# 我們這邊叫大彌猴桃
Here we call them big kiwifruits.
# 長大了就可以長那麼大的哦 這麼大 你看 這麼大
The fully grown ones can be that big, you know. That big, look? That big
# 這個還小 不能吃
This is still small. It can’t be eaten.
# 這個留給那個鳥吃
I’ll leave it for the birds.
# 鳥也吃了好多
The birds have also eaten a lot.
# 本來好多的 現在都掉啦
There should be a lot. But many have dropped.
# 上面還有幾個
Up there are a few more,.
# 都還不是很熟
But they’re not really that ripe.
# 看一下那邊有沒有
Let me see if there are any on that side.
# 你看 這裡有一個小海灘
Look! This is a small beach.
# 全是上面的沙子沖下來的哦
The sand is all washed from the upstream.
# 這沙子很好的
The sand here is really nice.
# 可以用來做房子的 這沙子
It can be used to build houses, the sand here.
# 沒甚麼雜質 全是小沙子
There are hardly any impurities, only fine sand.
# 這裡都是
Here as well
# 鑽都鑽不進來的 哇 這個
I can’t even squeeze in. Wa! This is…
# 好多哇
Really a lot!
# 一樹都是
They’re all over the tree!
# 這個掉下來啦
This one has dropped.
# 你看 這有6個
Look! Here are six.
# 好瘦哦 今年的拿藤果
They’re so skinny, the chocolate vine fruits this year,
# 今年的這個拿藤果 因為今年產量特高
the, the chocolate vine fruits this year. It’s because the yield is exceptionally high.
# 你看 這有竹節果哦
Look! Here are also wild mangosteens.
# 這個 肯定很酸的
This one, must be very sour.
# 哎呀
Aya!
# 你看 它冒汁
Look! The juice is bursting out.
# 這還沒熟
It’s not yet ripe.
# 捏都捏不動
I can’t even split it open.
# 算啦 給那個
Forget it. Let me leave it to the…
# 一樹都是
They’re all over the tree.
# 到時候 冬天的時候 我們就可以再過來這裡摘
Later, in winter, we can come again and pick them.
# 帶一個牛皮袋
Let's come with a bag.
# 這一棵要摘一牛皮袋
This tree can fill up a bag,
# 滿滿的 一樹都是
completely. The fruits are all over the tree.
# 你看 這裡又大又圓哦
Look! These are big and round.
# 這邊的 向陽光的地方稍微大一點
On this side, those facing the sunshine are a bit larger.
# 很多的
A lot!
# 旁邊還有一棵楊梅樹哦
Here’s also a bayberry tree next to it.
# 你看 吃了楊梅吃竹節果
Look! We can have wild mangosteens after having bayberries.
# 還可以喲 吃了竹節果又吃楊梅
Not bad! And come back to bayberries afterwards.
# 我們山上很多這樣的野果樹 (248)
There are a lot of these kinds of wild fruits on our hills.
# 野果還沒熟哇 我們路過兄弟家的玉米地
The wild fruits are not yet ripe. We pass by our buddy’s corn field.
# 他的玉米他不要的 他掰過一遍的
He has already harvested. The corns here are leftover.
# 剩下的都是營食不良的
Only the undernourished ones remain.
# 搞一點回去吃
Let me pick some back home.
# 那麼小的 概不得他不要
It’s so small. No wonder he doesn’t want them.
# 因為裡面的籽沒有多少 看到沒有
There’re not too many corns inside. See?
# 它的籽就只有一半的 還有一半都沒有的
These are only half-filled, or not even half-filled.
# 賣的話可能就不好賣
They can hardly be sold.
# 但它吃的是 吃的話就不影響口感哦
But when it comes to the taste, there’s no difference.
# 我搞一點回去吃
Let me pick some back home.
# 就搞了那麼幾個
So I’ve just picked a few here.
# 好多都沒肉的 一半肉都沒有的 概不得他不要
There’s hardly anything to eat. Most are not even half-filled. No wonder he doesn’t want them.
# 好啦
Alright!
# 回去煮玉米吃
Let’s go back and cook the corns.
# 一個月後
A month later
# 你看 這裡有個好黃的 又大又黃
Look! Here's a completely ripe one. It’s big and yellow.
# 看見沒有
See?
# 啊 看見沒有 好靚哦這個 還有
Ah! See? This one is really beautiful. There are more.
# 看到這裡上面 還有
I see some up there. There are more.
# 這個 有點黃的 要把它摘掉
This one, it's getting ripe. I need to pick it now.
# 你看這樹上好多黃哦
Look! Here are a lot of ripe ones in the tree.
# 你看 就摘了那麼一點點 打開來給大家看一下
Look! So we’ve picked just a tiny little bit. Let me open it and show you.
# 撒地上來
Just spill them onto the ground.
# 這兩個又大又黃的
These two are big and golden yellow.
# 我這個好吃
This one is really tasty.
# 這個味道很好的哦 很甜的
The taste is really good! It’s so sweet.
# 是那種又香又甜 又好吃的味道
It’s sort of, a combination of fragrance, sweetness, and good taste.
# 就像是 就是甜 好甜
It’s like, well, sweet, really sweet.
# 哎呀 吃不動
Aya! I can’t eat anymore.
# 多吃一點 這個爛掉啦
Let's eat more. This one is rotten.
# 你看這個 好香啊
Have a look at this one. It smells really good!
# 吃飽啦 撐不下去啦 等一下來
I’m really full. I can’t eat anymore now. Later.
# 到裡面 再慢慢吃
Put it here inside. I’ll eat it later.
# 你看這個小沙灘
Look! This small beach,
# 好多沙子啊這裡
here's a lot of sand.
# 你看這兩個 它在勾引我嗎
Have a look at these two. Are they flirting to me?
# 怎麼可以那黃 雙胞胎
How can they be so golden yellow! They’re twins.
# 看到沒有 靚吧
See? Beautiful, aren't they?
# 剝開 一人一個
Split them. Let’s have one each.
# 啊~
Ah~
# 嗯~好吃 不知道前面有沒有啦
Um~ Tasty! Let’s see if there are any more in the front.
# 你看這個 好大啊這個
Have a look at this one. This is really big!
# 掛住啦 不肯過來
It gets stuck. It doesn’t wanna come.
# 過來 過來
Come here! Come here!
# 你看
Look!
# 這個
This one,
this one,
# 肯定很好吃
must be very tasty.
# 那麼大
It’s so big.
# 放在這裡 我看下裡面有沒有
Leave it here. Let me see if there any down there.
# 你看 這裡有
Look! Some more here
# 誒呦
Eyo!
# 兩個都被鳥吃啦 還有一個
These two were eaten by the birds. Only one left
# 你看這個鳥 我跟它有感情的哦
Look! The birds, we have really good relationship, you know.
# 我不吃這兩個 還有一個就給我吃
I’m not eating these two. And one is left for me.
# 這還有一個
Here’s one more.
# 你看是不是
Look! Am I right?
# 我留給它吃 它留給我吃
I leave them fruits, and they leave me fruits as well.
# 這兩個也是爛的
These two are also rotten.
# 你看這個就好的
Look! This one is nice.
# 這有一個 有點爛啦
Here’s one. It’s a bit rotten.
# 哇 又大又黃的哦
Ah! It’s big and ripe, you know.
# 太好吃啦
Simply delicious!
# 這裡差不多一百多斤 哎呀 應該沒有一百斤
Here is more than fifty kilograms. Aya! No, I think not yet fifty.
# 可能差不多 接近 一牛皮袋
But it should be close, almost. You know, a whole bag.
# 是呀 還蠻多的 哎呀
Yea! We’ve quite a lot here. Aya!
# 我要把這個搞完啦
Don’t break this thing.
# 搬回去
Let’s take it back.
# 剛好搞野果 路過兄弟家的那個果園 一大片都是哦
We’ve just finished picking the wild fruits and now we pass by our buddy’s orchard. It’s the whole area here.
# 這裡最少能產個 七八 七八十萬斤吧
Here can yield at least, three, four, three or four hundred thousand kilograms, right?
# 應該有那麼多 你看 那邊那邊那邊 裡面還有哦
Yea! I think so. Look! There, there, there and more inside.
# 這邊快黃啦
Those on this side are becoming ripe very soon.
# 這邊是向陽的地方
They’re facing the sunshine on this side.
# 這裡 這裡再過十天應該就可以摘啦
I think these, these can be picked in ten days.
# 你看這裡 全是標準果哦 不大又不小 剛剛好
Look! The oranges here are all in standard size. Not too big, not too small. Just right
# 這種果其實洗都不用洗的哦
In fact these oranges don’t need to be washed at all, you know.
# 摘下來就直接裝箱 這樣它就更新鮮
They can be boxed right away from the tree. This can retain the freshness.
# 你看 這個果很漂亮吧這個
Look! This orange is really pretty, isn’t it?
# 不大不小 剛剛好哦 這種
The size is just right, perfect, this one.
# 還沒熟
But it’s not yet ripe.
# 不是 現在已經可以 可以吃了 但是有點
No! In fact, it can already be, can be eaten now. But it may be a bit,
# 可能還有點酸 酸酸甜甜的
it may be a bit sour, sweet and sour.
# 等到它全部 整個 象這種顏色的時候
We gotta wait, until all, the whole orange, is in this colour.
# 那就是黃了 熟透了 那個才是真正的臍橙
Then it is ripe, completely ripe. And it will be an authentic navel orange.
# 剛剛來到兄弟家 他說他不在呦
We’ve just arrived at our buddy’s place. But it said that he’s not here.
# 關也關著的
The gates are also closed.
# 你看 他的臍橙 那麼多臍橙他也不看一下
Look! His navel oranges. He has so many oranges but he’s not watching them.
# 就不怕我摘
Doesn’t he know that I may be picking them?
# 真是的
Unbelievable!
# 那麼多
There are so many!
# 順便叫他送一點給我吃
Why don’t we ask him to give us some?
# 乾趴趴的 搞了一天
I’m fatigue. A whole day, non-stop!
# 吃的又太飽了
And I’ve also eaten too much.
# 把它倒出來
Let me pour them out.
# 哎呀 全部爆掉啦
Aya! All are cracked,
# 爛掉的爛掉 爆掉的爆掉 你看這個
either rotten, or cracked. Have a look at this one!
# 這種就好吃噠 這種
This one is really tasty, this kind.
# 我都至少吃了二三十個啦
I’ve eaten at least twenty or thirty already.
# 也給點兄弟
Let me leave some for my buddy.
# 好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
# 等下兄弟會過來 自己拿 叫他帶個鴨子殺一下
My buddy will be coming in a while. He’ll take the fruits himself. Let me ask him to bring a duck here for us.
# 搞的那麼累
It's really tiring.